{
  "reference_number": "9196",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "Emissions from almost every aspect of our everyday living are complex and generally inter-related. It will take a lot of time and effort to\n\n unravel these and establish a solution that has the least economical impact for the greatest gain. While a time target is important but\n not to the extent that decisions are compromised by time constraints."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "Emission from processes that use the reduction of metal oxides to the metals we at least need in the next 50 years all produce\n carbon dioxide. Air transport produces huge quantities of CO2, 1 kg of fuel burnt = 3.15 kg of CO2 at high altitude where it takes time\n to fall to ground or sea level to be converted to carbon and oxygen in plant life to highlight just a couple of major issues."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "New forests take time to prepare, plant & grow to the point where significant quantities can be converted, limiting uptake in the initial\n time set periods. I am concerned that trading in carbon credits by financial traders can escalate costs with no real input to the\n environmental issues."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The interrelated issues will be complex so as they evolve, the time line may need to be adjusted in respect to some specific issue or\n issues to achieve the best outcome. After all what is the use of fixing the environment if we can not live here."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The financial impact must be established and budgets set in place as the remedial issues evolve."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "To ensure that there is an on-going responsibility toward the objective."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "See above. The issues will take time to evolve, there respective impacts, remedial actions and the related costs."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "While it is good to have a statement (an objective) at the outset, this should be able to be refined and adjusted as the issues are\ndefined in detail and solutions established so that hasty actions are taken that can have adverse impact elsewhere at a later date. We\nare still suffering from legislation that impacted on leaky buildings made from untreated timber to name one example from the\n\nindustry I have been involved in."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We must be kept informed on the issues and solutions, not knee jerk type proclamations 'from the throne'."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Consult with the regions to establish all the issues as they apply to that region. One fix will not fit all. Auckland's issues are very\n\ndifferent to Westlands. We have very low CO2 emissions and large biomass uptake while Auckland is exactly the opposite."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The issues are very complex and inter-related as banning one item, say oil can have a flow on effect to medical issues, lubrication for\n\ntransport issues, energy replacement issues for transport, industrial and commercial processing, heating and so on & on & on, to\nname just one."
    }
  ]
}
